<documentation>
    <page>
        <title>ProdUI Theme System</title>
    </page>

    <page>
		<title>Skins</title>

		Widgets can be customized by developing new skins.

		SkinDef: Defines a skin.

		SkinInstance: A "live" copy of a SkinDef, with references assigned, numbers scaled, and other such transformations applied.


		<title>Resource Management</title>

		The SkinDef registry is a weak table (both keys and values). This allows the theming system to manage temporary SkinDefs without the need for additional bookkeeping when they are no longer referenced by anything. All SkinDefs loaded from disk are preserved by being stored in a secondary table that is not weak.


		<title>Marking resources for transformation</title>

		SkinDef fields beginning with an asterisk (<pre>self["*foobar"]</pre>) contain strings that indicate where a particular resource can be found within the theme instance's table hierarchy. The reference is assigned in the skin instance to a copy of the field without the leading asterisk:

		<pre>
		self["*foobar"] = "path/to/foobar"
		self.foobar = **resource pulled in from resources.path.to.foobar**

		self["*bazbop"] = {"multiple/paths", "to/various", "textures/used"}
		self.bazbop = **array containing three resources**
		</pre>

		This is used when refreshing the contents of SkinInstances.

		Fields beginning with a dollar sign (<pre>self["$foobar"]</pre>) contain numbers which are automatically scaled:

		<pre>
		self["$foobar"] = 32
		self.foobar = **math.floor(32 * theme.scale)**

		self["$bazbop"] = {32, 64}
		self.bazbop = <{math.floor(32 * theme.scale), math.floor(64 * theme.scale)}>
		</pre>


		<title>Box Styles</title>

		Fields:

		* sl_body_id: The ID of a 9-Slice texture which should be rendered with the box. Used to unify the look of panels and context menus. Not all boxes include this
		field.

		* outpad {x1, y1, x2, y2}: The intended amount of outer padding around the box. Sometimes used by the layout system. Does not affect the widget's width and height directly. Similar to "margin" in HTML/CSS.

		* border {x1, y1, x2, y2}: A border that starts at the widget's edge and grows inward. Usually precludes scroll bars, and may be used to designate a widget's draggable edges. Similar to "border" in HTML/CSS.

		* margin {x1, y1, x2, y2}: Inner padding which begins at the border and grows inward. Similar to "padding" in HTML/CSS.
	</page>

</documentation>
